

Shaopeng Liu

Ph.D. candidate **Bioinformatics**

sml6467@psu.edu

+1 3145852220



State College, PA, 16803



PDF: Curriculum vitae

Keywords -

- 1. Bioinformatician
- 2. Genomic data scientist
- 3. Metagenomics
- 4. Biomedical knowledge graphs

Skills —— Python Shell Genomics & NGS

Machine Learning

Statistics

Algorithm

Docker & Git

SQL

Summary

Passionate bioinformatician with 5+ years experience analyzing genomic datasets and computational tasks. Developed and implemented comprehensive pipelines and novel algorithms. Currently working on sketching-based algorithms and graph learning methods for metagenomic samples. Seeking to leverage efficient algorithms, multi-omic data, artificial intelligence, and biomedical knowledge graphs to address health-related issues.

Education

2019-2024 Ph.D. in Bioinformatics & Genomics 2016-2017 M.Sc. in Biostatistics 2010-2014 B.Sc. in Biology

Pennsylvania State University Washington University in St. Louis **Wuhan University**

Experience

- 1. Bioinformatic intern (2022.5-8, Gilead Sciences)
 - developed k-mer-based algorithms for HBV genotyping of clinical samples.
- 2. Doctoral researcher in computational biology (2020-2024, PSU)
 - · proved, implemented, and benchmarked a truncation-based containment Min-Hash algorithm CMash for multi-resolution estimation of Jaccard and containment indices in metagenomic analysis;
 - worked in the Biomedical Data Translator Consortium that aims at providing a graph-based reasoning tool for biomedical and translational studies;
 - utilized k-mer-sketching-based methods to develop comprehensive pipelines to explore the "microbial dark matter";
 - besides the sketching methods, adopted graph learning methods to analyze microbial samples for pathogen detection.
- 3. Bioinformatician (2017-2019, WUSTL)
 - collaborated with various groups and performed bioinformatic analysis on genomic and epigenomic datasets, including ChIP-seq, RNA-seq, WGBS, ATACseq, and single-cell RNA;
 - · worked in the Data Coordination Center (DCC) of TaRGET II Consortium, streamlined and setup the routine pipelines for RNA-seq, ChIP-seq, WGBS, and ATACseq data; and processed part of data with preliminary quality analysis;
 - · developed AIAP, an advanced ATAC-seq analysis pipeline for comprehensive analysis of ATAC-seq dataset; and also implemented the pipeline into Docker and Singularity

Publication

2022	Biolink Model: A universal schema for knowledge graphs in clinical, biomedical, and translational science[J]. <i>Clinical and Translational Science</i>
2022	Progress toward a universal biomedical data translator[J]. <i>Clinical and Translational Science</i>
2022	ARAX: a graph-based modular reasoning tool for translational biomedicine. <i>bioRxiv</i>
2022	*CMash: fast, multi-resolution estimation of k-mer-based Jaccard

*AIAP: A Quality Control and Integrative Analysis Package to Improve ATAC-seq Data Analysis. Genomics, Proteomics & Bioinformatics

and containment indices. Bioinformatics

*: first author

2021



Shaopeng Liu

Ph.D. candidate Bioinformatics

sml6467@psu.edu

a

+1 3145852220



State College, PA, 16803



PDF: Curriculum vitae

Keywords -

- 1. Bioinformatician
- 2. Genomic data scientist
- 3. Metagenomics
- 4. Biomedical knowledge graphs

Skills -

Shell

Genomics & NGS

Machine Learning

Statistics

Algorithm

Docker & Git

SQL

2021	Deconstructing Stepwise Fate Conversion of Human Fibroblasts to Neurons by MicroRNAs. <i>CELL STEM CELL</i>
2020	Comparison of differential accessibility analysis strategies for ATAC-seq data. <i>Scientific reports</i>
2019	Conditional Activation of NF- κ B Inducing Kinase (NIK) in the Osteolineage Enhances Both Basal and Loading-Induced Bone Formation. Journal of Bone and Mineral Research
2018	The role of Twist1 in mutant huntingtin-induced transcriptional alterations and neurotoxicity. <i>Journal of Biological Chemistry</i>
2017	Regulatory networks specifying cortical interneurons from human embryonic stem cells reveal roles for CHD2 in interneuron development. <i>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</i>
2014	Multistage Regulator Based on Tandem Promoters and CRISPR/Cas. ACS Synthetic Biology

Awards

2019-2021	The Graham Endowed Fel	lowship	Pennsylvania State University
2019	The J. Lloyd Huck Gradua	te Fellowship	Pennsylvania State University
2019	The Braddock Scholarshi	р	Pennsylvania State University
2016	WU Scholarship and Gran	its	Washington University in St. Louis
2013	Golden medal	International Gene	tically Engineered Machine (IGEM)
2010-2012	College Scholarship		Wuhan University